<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-31T16:52:39+00:00</updated><id>https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Paris RNA Club</title><subtitle>Paris RNA Club </subtitle><entry><title type="html">We are thrilled to announce our next speakers: Olivia CHARMANT and Carine TISNE</title><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2024/10/10/tabs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We are thrilled to announce our next speakers: Olivia CHARMANT and Carine TISNE"/><published>2024-10-10T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2024/10/10/tabs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2024/10/10/tabs.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: 1.5em;"><strong>Olivia CHARMANTt</strong></span><br/> Sandra DUHARCOURT’s lab - Élimination programmée du génome, Institut Jacques Monod</p> <p><strong>Title</strong>:<br/> The PIWI-interacting protein Gtsf1 controls the selective degradation of small RNAs in Paramecium</p> <p><strong>Abstract</strong>:<br/> Ciliates undergo developmentally programmed genome elimination, in which small RNAs direct the removal of transposable elements during the development of the somatic nucleus. 25-nt scnRNAs are produced from the entire germline genome and transported to the maternal somatic nucleus, where selection of scnRNAs corresponding to germline-specific sequences is thought to take place. Selected scnRNAs then guide the elimination of transposable elements in the developing somatic nucleus. How germline-specific scnRNAs are selected remains to be determined. Here, we provide important mechanistic insights into the scnRNA selection pathway by identifying a Paramecium homolog of Gtsf1 as essential for the selective degradation of scnRNAs corresponding to retained somatic sequences. Consistently, we also show that Gtsf1 is localized in the maternal somatic nucleus where it associates with the scnRNA-binding protein Ptiwi09. Furthermore, we demonstrate that the scnRNA selection process is critical for genome elimination. We propose that Gtsf1 is required for the coordinated degradation of Ptiwi09-scnRNA complexes that pair with target RNA via the ubiquitin pathway, similarly to the mechanism suggested for microRNA target-directed degradation in metazoans.<br/><br/></p> <p><span style="font-size: 1.5em;"><strong>Carine TISNE</strong></span><br/> Institut de biologie physico-chimique</p> <p><strong>Title</strong>: TBC</p> <p><strong>Abstract</strong>:<br/> TBC</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Olivia CHARMANTt Sandra DUHARCOURT’s lab - Élimination programmée du génome, Institut Jacques Monod]]></summary></entry></feed>