<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-23T13:39:35+00:00</updated><id>https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Paris RNA Club</title><subtitle>Paris RNA Club </subtitle><entry><title type="html">A51 startup and Dr Arantxa Rojas (Germano Cecere’s lab)</title><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2025/11/26/tabs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A51 startup and Dr Arantxa Rojas (Germano Cecere’s lab)"/><published>2025-11-26T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-26T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2025/11/26/tabs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2025/11/26/tabs.html"><![CDATA[<p>Arantxa Rojas Mechanisms of Epigenetic Inheritance, Department of Developmental and Stem Cell Biology, Institut Pasteur, CNRS UMR3738, Paris. Postdoc in Germano Cecere’s lab</p> <p>Title: Nuclear Argonaute HRDE-1 Maintains Chromatin-Independent Transcriptional Silencing through a Transgenerational Small RNA Feedback Loop</p> <p>Abstract: Epigenetic inheritance of transcriptional silencing is traditionally attributed to chromatin- based mechanisms in which Argonaute–small RNA complexes recruit histone-modifying enzymes. In this project, we found that in Caenorhabditis elegans, the nuclear Argonaute HRDE-1 maintains germline transcriptional repression independently of canonical heterochromatin marks. Using inducible, germline-specific HRDE-1 depletion combined with nuclear sorting, CUT&amp;Tag, and nascent transcription profiling, we identified endogenous genes that become transcriptionally activated upon loss of HRDE-1 despite retaining H3K9me3 and H3K23me3. HRDE-1 directly restrains RNA polymerase II (Pol II) while simultaneously promoting antisense small RNA production in perinuclear condensates, thereby coupling nuclear transcriptional repression to small RNA biogenesis. HRDE-1 loss causes progressive erosion of antisense small RNAs and delays silencing re-establishment, revealing a transgenerational feedback loop in which small RNAs, and not chromatin modifications, constitute the primary heritable signal. These findings redefine nuclear Argonautes as active drivers of RNA-based epigenetic inheritance and broaden our understanding of how small RNA pathways maintain transcriptional silencing across generations.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Arantxa Rojas Mechanisms of Epigenetic Inheritance, Department of Developmental and Stem Cell Biology, Institut Pasteur, CNRS UMR3738, Paris. Postdoc in Germano Cecere’s lab]]></summary></entry></feed>