<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-21T08:34:22+00:00</updated><id>https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Paris RNA Club</title><subtitle>Paris RNA Club </subtitle><entry><title type="html">We are thrilled to announce our next speakers: Dr Eric ALLEMAND and Dr Martin DUTERTRE</title><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2025/03/13/tabs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We are thrilled to announce our next speakers: Dr Eric ALLEMAND and Dr Martin DUTERTRE"/><published>2025-03-13T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-13T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2025/03/13/tabs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2025/03/13/tabs.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: 1.5em;"><strong>Eric ALLEMAND</strong></span><br/> Laboratory of cellular and molecular mechanisms of hematological disorders and therapeutic implications, U1163-CEREMAST, Foundation IMAGINE</p> <p><strong>Title</strong>:<br/> Regulation of transcriptome diversity through alternative splicing and its role in hematological genetic disorders.</p> <p><strong>Abstract</strong>:<br/> RNA processing, particularly alternative splicing, regulates nearly all human genes and is a key contributor to gene expression diversity. Splicing defects are implicated in around 35% of genetic diseases and play an important role in cellular transformation, especially in cancers arising from impaired hematopoietic differentiation. In myelodysplastic syndromes and mastocytosis, pathogenic mutations frequently target splicing factors, while widespread splicing deregulation is observed in leukemia and lymphoma. Although high-throughput Exome and Whole Genome Sequencing (WGS) with short-read technologies have revolutionized mutation detection, these methods are inherently limited in their capacity to thoroughly analyze splicing defects. We are developing projects that aim to unravel splicing dysregulation in hematological disorders using Third Generation Sequencing (TGS) technologies. Our focus is particularly directed toward transcripts whose expression constitutes a minor fraction of the full repertoire of splice variants. These approaches reveal an underappreciated diversity in the transcriptome that is often missed by conventional genetic analyses. Our work seeks to identify novel pathological markers linked to splicing regulation, explore their functional impacts, and develop corrective tools to address these defects. We work on: Identification of aberrant splice-driven signature in T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Reprogramming the post-transcriptional regulation of BCL11A to treat β-hemoglobinopathies. Global analysis of alternative splicing in erythropoiesis: unveiling novel therapeutic approaches to β-hemoglobinopathies.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Eric ALLEMAND Laboratory of cellular and molecular mechanisms of hematological disorders and therapeutic implications, U1163-CEREMAST, Foundation IMAGINE]]></summary></entry></feed>