<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-06T12:20:22+00:00</updated><id>https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Paris RNA Club</title><subtitle>Paris RNA Club </subtitle><entry><title type="html">We are thrilled to announce our next speakers: Dr Loic BROIX and Dr Patricia UGUEN</title><link href="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2025/06/19/tabs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We are thrilled to announce our next speakers: Dr Loic BROIX and Dr Patricia UGUEN"/><published>2025-06-19T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-19T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2025/06/19/tabs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.parisrnaclub.fr//2025/06/19/tabs.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: 1.5em;"><strong>Loic BROIX</strong></span><br/></p> <p><strong>Title</strong>:<br/> TBA</p> <p><strong>Abstract</strong>:<br/> TBA</p> <p><span style="font-size: 1.5em;"><strong>Patricia UGUEN</strong></span><br/> CNRS UMR3348 Genome integrity, RNA and Cancer, Institut Curie, University Paris-Saclay</p> <p><strong>Title</strong>: Does 53BP1 bind to RNA-DNA primers to prevent the activation of innate immune response?</p> <p><strong>Abstract</strong>:<br/> Genomic instability has many incomes, either endogenous or exogenous sources. In addition to pathogenic DNA, self-DNA, which are accumulated in cytosol can activate innate immune responses, leading to the production of type 1 interferon (IFN) stimulated genes (ISG). This activation would be mediated by the cGAS-STING pathway. 53BP1 is well known as a mediator of the double-strand break repair, but it is also involved into fork protection under replicative stress. The team has recently found that 53BP1 protein binds to RNA-DNA primers in unperturbated DNA replication. We ask whether the binding activity of 53BP1 can play a protective role against uncontrolled release of RNA- DNA chimeras. We have shown that depletion of 53BP1 activates expression of many markers of inflammatory type I interferons.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Loic BROIX]]></summary></entry></feed>